mrt-rrt.gov.au 2015-06-22

# MRT-RRT - Privacy

This Privacy Policy applies to personal information collected by the Migration Review Tribunal (MRT) and the Refugee Review Tribunal (RRT). The MRT-RRT (the tribunals) are bound by provisions relating to the collection, use and disclosure of personal information by various Commonwealth laws – particularly the _Migration Act 1958_ (the Migration Act) and the _Privacy Act 1988_ (the Privacy Act).

**Outline of this policy**  
'Part A — Personal Information handling practices’ explains our general information handling practices and obligations.  
‘Part B – Personal Information handling Practices under the Migration Act’ explains how we handle personal information during the review process and when publishing decisions.  
'Part C — Files' offers further detail by explaining our personal information handling practices in relation to specific activities such as merits review, Freedom of Information and human resource management. Here you can find out what sort of records we keep and why. You may find this section helpful if, for example, you have made an application for review to the tribunals and wish to know how we manage our case files.  
'Part D — Online' explains our personal information handling practices when you visit our website.

##  Part A — Personal information handling practices

As an Australian Government agency, we are bound by the [Australian Privacy Principles](http://www.comlaw.gov.au/Details/C2014C00076/Html/Text#_Toc382303234) (

APPs

) in the Privacy Act which regulate how agencies may collect, use, disclose and store personal information, and how individuals may access and correct personal information held about them.

###  Collection

We collect personal information for purposes which are directly related to our functions or activities under the Migration Act and only when it is necessary for or directly related to such purposes. In providing personal/sensitive information to the tribunals you are taken to have given consent to the collection and use of that information for purposes under the Migration Act. The tribunals will collect personal/sensitive information about persons in connection with a review. The tribunals will not issue a separate privacy notice on each instance of collecting/using such information.

We also collect personal information related to employment services, human resource management, and other corporate service functions which are reasonably necessary for us to carry out our functions under the Migration Act and which are directly related to functions and activities under other Commonwealth legislation.

###  Use and disclosure of personal information

We use or disclose personal information for the purposes for which we collected it, namely for the purpose of conducting reviews.

  We may also use or disclose personal information generally:

  * for reasonably expected secondary purposes that are related or directly related to the primary purpose; or
  * for other purposes permitted by law; or
  * with the consent of the individual.

In certain circumstances we may provide information about applications for review to other government agencies or other entities. These include but are not limited to the Department of Immigration and Border Protection (the department), the Office of the MARA, the Commonwealth Ombudsman, the Australian Human Rights Commission, courts and tribunals and law enforcement agencies.

On occasions, we disclose personal information to overseas recipients during hearings when taking evidence from a witness who is overseas or in the course of an investigation undertaken by the department at the request of the tribunals. 

###  Accuracy and security of personal information held by us

We will endeavour to ensure that personal information sought and held by the tribunals is relevant, accurate, complete and up-to-date.

We use a range of physical and electronic security measures to protect personal information from misuse and loss, and from unauthorised access, modification or disclosure. These measures include, but are not limited to, restricted physical access to our offices, secure databases, computer-user identifiers and passwords.

###  Access to (and correction of) personal information held by us

You can access the personal information that we hold about you. We will provide access unless we consider that there is a sound reason under the Privacy Act, the _Freedom of Information Act 1982_ (the FOI Act) or any other relevant Acts including the Migration Act to withhold the information. You can also ask us to correct the personal information we hold about you under the FOI Act. If we refuse to give access to or to correct personal information held by us, we will provide you with written reasons for the refusal.   
For more information about how to request access to personal information and your available options, see the MRT-RRT web page ‘[Access to information](http://www.mrt-rrt.gov.au/About-Us/Access-to-information.aspx#Freedomofinformation)’.  

###  How to make a complaint or inquiry

If you wish to find out more about how we manage personal information or if you have a concern regarding the way in which we handle your personal information and wish to make a complaint, please contact us:  
Email: [complaints@mrt-rrt.gov.au](mailto:complaints@mrt-rrt.gov.au)  
Phone: 02 9276 5000  
Address: GPO Box 1333  
Sydney NSW 2001

  The tribunals’ procedures for dealing with complaints are available on the website under [Feedback and complaints](http://www.mrt-rrt.gov.au/About-Us/Feedback-and-complaints.aspx).

###  Handling privacy breaches

The tribunals have a guideline that outlines the procedures to be followed where a breach of the Privacy Act occurs.

##  Part B – Personal information handling practices under the Migration Act

###  During merits review

The Migration Act has particular provisions relating to the collection and use of personal information. These include:

  * Requirements not to make a record of, or divulge or communicate, personal information other than for a purpose of the Migration Act, or for the purposes of, or in connection with, the performance of a function or duty or the exercise of a power under the Migration Act (sections 377 and 439).
  * A requirement not to publicly identify any applicant for a protection visa or any relative or other dependent of an applicant for a protection visa (section 431(2) of the Migration Act).Subject to certain exceptions, the tribunals must provide adverse information to an applicant for comment if the information would form the reason, or part of the reason, for affirming the decision under review.  In some circumstances, this may be personal information of a third party who provided the adverse information or who is identified in the information (sections 359AA/359A and 424AA/424A).
  * The Migration Act requires that proceedings of the MRT generally be open to the public (section 365) and that all proceedings of the RRT be held in private (section 429).

###  Publishing decisions

The tribunals are required to publish decisions that are considered to be of 'particular interest'. The requirement to publish decisions is subject to certain restrictions set out in the Migration Act. Published decisions are available on the [Australasian Legal Information Institute's (AustLII's) website](http://www.austlii.edu.au/ "External link to Australian Legal Information Institute").

##  Part C — Files

###  1\. Case files and Case Management System

The purpose of the case files is to record action the MRT and RRT take under the Migration Act in reviewing visa and visa related decisions, and to record information relevant to these reviews.  The tribunals’ computerised Case Management System also records and stores a significant proportion of the information kept on case files, and audio recordings of hearings.

  Personal information may include name, contact details, date of birth, gender, nationality and marital status of review applicants, visa applicants and their relatives and information submitted by the applicants in support of their claims. The content may also include name and contact details of persons appointed by applicants as their representatives and/or their authorised recipients for correspondence and of witnesses.

Sensitive personal information received by the tribunals may include information about a person’s racial or ethnical origin, political opinions, membership of a particular association, religious beliefs or affiliations, philosophical beliefs, membership of a profession, trade association or trade union, sexual orientation or practices, criminal record, health information, genetic information and biometric information.

The personal information on these records relates to applications for review. Persons mentioned on the case files may include the applicant, family members, authorised recipients or representatives, any witnesses and other persons relevant to the application. Files can also include the names of tribunal members, staff and interpreters.

All members and staff who are involved in the review process and information technology personnel have access to this information.  Information technology service providers involved in the on-going development and maintenance of the case management system also have access to this information.

###  2\. Finance records and Financial Management Information System (SAP/R3)

The purpose of these records is to administer the operations and finances of the tribunals.  
The personal information on these records relates to anyone who has financial dealings with the tribunals. Content may include name, address, telephone number, facsimile number, email address, whether the person is a debtor or creditor and bank account details.

The records are stored on paper and computer media. Finance systems are password protected and access is confined to tribunals’ Finance Section staff on finance computer equipment. Hard copy records are kept in secure storage, accessible only by finance staff.

###  3\. Personnel records

The purpose of these records is to record and maintain personnel information for business and employment related purposes, or where authorised or required by law. Content includes name, address, age, next of kin, salary, and other relevant entitlement data. Content may also include sensitive personal information such as medical information.

The tribunals’ officers with access to full staff information are those in Human Resources Section. The information may also be accessed for technical reasons by a limited number of Information Technology senior administrators.

Tribunal members and officers are able to access their personal records such as pay details, payroll history, leave taken and future leave requests by way of an Employee Self Service (ESS) system.  The ESS system is a password protected computer media enabling employee’s access to this limited data. Tribunal staff and members are also able to amend aspects of their own records such as personal address details and emergency contact information via this system. Additionally, managers, team leaders and senior members have access to leave history and leave requests for their direct staff using the ESS system and some payroll information by way of other reports/systems.

###  4\. Procurement and tender records

The purpose of these records is to administer tenders received in response to a request for tender. The personal information on these records relates to potential contractors. Content may include name, address, occupation, biographical/financial details and referees names and their comments and reports on tenderers.

The following members and staff have access to this information: Principal Member, Registrar, Deputy Registrars _,_ Director of Finance and Business Services, Assistant Director of Business Services and members and staff involved in procurement and in the assessment of tenders.

The tribunals are required to publish certain information in relation to successful tenders on the AusTender website <https://www.tenders.gov.au/>. Where the successful tender is worth more than $100,000 certain information is also included on the tribunals’ website <http://www.mrt-rrt.gov.au/>.  Confidentiality requirements are considered prior to publishing tender related information on websites. The tribunals publish details of any consultants engaged in annual reports. 

Separate records are kept in relation to the procurement of legal services from external legal services providers and management of external legal services procurement.  The personal information in these records relates to potential service providers and may also relate to parties to legal proceedings involving the tribunal and other persons named in documentation associated with such proceedings. Content may include name, address, occupation, biographical details and other personal information in documents associated with legal proceedings.  

The following members and staff have access to this information: Principal Member, Registrar, Deputy Registrars _,_ Director of Legal Services and staff involved in procurement of external legal services and management of external legal services providers.

###  5\. Freedom of information requests

The tribunals maintain a register and files of all FOI requests. Content may include name, address, telephone number, facsimile number, email address and background details of FOI applicants.

The following members and staff have access to this information: Principal Member, Registrar, Deputy Principal Member, Deputy Registrars _,_ Director of Legal Services and members and staff involved in the handling of FOI requests.

###  6\. Complaints and general enquiries

The tribunals maintain a register and files of formal complaints and general enquiries.  
The following members and staff have access to this information: Principal Member, Registrar, Deputy Principal Member, Deputy Registrars _,_ Director of Legal Services and members and staff involved in the handling of complaints and enquiries.

###  7\. Mailing and community liaison meeting lists

The mailing list contains details of individuals and agencies that have an interest in migration and protection review matters and who have requested to receive information about the tribunal.  The list is used principally to disseminate information and to arrange community liaison meetings. The community liaison meeting list contains details of individuals and agencies who are invited to tribunal community liaison meetings. Content may include name, job title, organisation, postal address, telephone number, email address and facsimile number.

The following members and staff have access to this information: Principal Member, Registrar, Deputy Principal Member, Deputy Registrars _,_ Director of Legal Services and staff involved in procurement of external legal services and management of external legal services providers.

##  Part D — Online

###  Website visits

The tribunals do not collect personal information about you when you visit the tribunals’ website. When a person visits our website, we make a record (in server logs) of information such as the network address, the pages accessed and documents downloaded and the type of browser used, for statistical and network management purposes. This website stores information in 'cookies' on your computer, however they are not used to collect personal information.

###  Email addresses

The tribunals will only record your email address if you send us an email message or otherwise provide us with your email address. It will not be added to a mailing list. If you are listed on one or more of our email subscriber lists you can opt out at any time. You can unsubscribe by using the ‘unsubscribe’ options noted in our emails.  

###  Online applications

The tribunals use web-based online application systems for lodging applications for review and for submitting job applications. Personal information collected through these online application systems are used and disclosed in accordance with this Privacy Policy.  

Back to top
